<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Notusknot's website</title>
        <link>https://notusknot.com</link>
        <description>Notusknot's blog; linux, programming, music, and whatever else I want</description>
        <language>en-us</language>
    <!-- bmanager -->
<item><title>Software i use</title><guid>https://notusknot.com/posts/software-i-use</guid><link>https://notusknot.com/posts/software-i-use</link><pubDate>November 14, 2021</pubDate><description> <![CDATA[ <h1> Software I use </h1>

<h2> Operating system </h2>

<h3> GNU/Linux (specifically NixOS)</h3>

<p class="articleP">
So I've been using Linux for a while now (I know it's GNU/Linux but I'll call it Linux just for simplicity). Like most other people, 
I started off on Windows, but then switched to Linux and have stayed on it ever since. I first switched because I liked Solus's interface a lot, 
and after trying it out on a live USB stick I liked it so much so I just installed it. Nowadays I choose it over Windows and MacOS for a lot of reasons,
include:
    <ul>
        <li> Linux is free: One of the main philosophies of GNU/Linux is that it's free, and not in the way that you think. Of course it is free as in 
            zero cost, but also free as in all (most) of the code is licensed under a free license, and readily avaiable for the public to look over and modify.
            This is a whole other world to dive into, but basically, this lets you insure your OS is secure, not spying on you, and if there are any changes you
            dislike, you can just change them yourself. </li>
        <li> Customizability: Linux being free gives you far more control over your OS. On Windows I was either forced to pay $120 for a license, or live
            with a watermark in the corner at all times and far fewer interface customization options. Of course you can always pirate these licenses, but I
            don't think people should need to commit a crime to have a decent OS. On Linux I can basicically change whatever I want, which is a really nice 
            to have feature. I've chosen and modified my own window manager, terminal, text editor, and a bunch of other stuff that is locked behind an iron 
            wall in Windows and MacOS. </li>
        <li> Great software: one of the biggest complaints for Linux is that it doesn't support a bunch of software. While this is somewhat true (a lot of 
            the apps you think aren't suppported probably have some workaround on Linux), the majority of the time, Linux has an alternative that is as good,
            or usually better than what's on Windows. For example, the password manager I use on a daily basis, <a href="https://www.passwordstore.org/" target="_blank">pass</a>
            is (as far as I know) only avaiable on Linux, and much better than any other proprietary password manager I've used before on Windows. I'll go more into
                good software I use later in the article. </li>
        <li> Secure: Linux being open source makes it inhererently more secure than closed source operating systems. When you have thousands of eyes scrutinizing
            a codebase, you are much more likely to find and fix any potential security bugs. Linux's is also just more secure by default.
        <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZYWPyTRXssg" target="_blank">This video</a> is a good explanation. </li>
        <li> Minimal: one of my biggest issues with Windows is that it is bloated and contains a ton of junk I don't want. It even has <a href="https://www.pcmag.com/how-to/how-to-remove-the-most-annoying-ads-in-windows-10" target="_blank">
            ads in the start menu.</a> Sure, you can take them out, but that shouldn't even be an issue you have to go out of your way to solve. Windows
            is also a total resource hog. I tested out a completely fresh install of Windows in a VM, and the first boot took around 2 GB of RAM with no
                apps open other than Task Manager. My install of NixOS with dwm regularly uses 300-350 MB of RAM on a fresh boot. </li>
    </ul>
</p>

<h3> OS utilities </h3>

<p class="articleP">
I tend to go for stuff that follows the Unix philosophy: do one thing, and do it well. Here's a list of regular OS utilities I use:
    <ul>
        <li> Window manager: dwm. It does what I want it to do, with no hassle or bloat. </li>
        <li> Terminal emulator: st. It's not perfect, but good enough for me and does what it needs to. </li>
        <li> Text editor: neovim. Vim is great, and neovim is even better. I love the Lua configuration, native LSP, keybinds, and so much other stuff. </li>
        <li> File browser: GNU coreutils (ls, mv, etc). I don't really see a need for a file browser, just using the terminal tends to be faster for me. </li>
        <li> Web browser: I bounce between Firefox and Brave Browser. Both are open-source and relatively privacy-respecting out of the box, but neither are perfect.
            I like Firefox for its Reader Mode, customizability, and about:config options. I like Brave for it's BAT system, Speedreader, and out-of-the-box ad-blocking. </li>
        <li> Shell: zsh. Honestly, I just use it because I like how it looks. It has some annoying things and I'll probably replace it some day. </li>
        <li> Crypto: the only thing that isn't open source on this list: Exodus wallet. I really like the interface, and it's non-custodial, meaning no KYC and
            higher security than exchanges like Coinbase. </li>
        <li> Other stuff: mpv for videos, zathura for PDFs, and newsboat for RSS feeds. I don't use these very often though. </li>
    </ul>
</p>]]></description></item>
        <item><title>First article</title><guid>https://notusknot.com/posts/first-article</guid><link>https://notusknot.com/posts/first-article</link><pubDate>August 28, 2021</pubDate><description><![CDATA[
<h2> How I made my website </h2>

<p> 
I've wanted to make a website for a long time, and after some learning
and practice, that is finally a reality :). In my very first blog post, I'll
go over the philosophy and ideas for this website, how I actually made it,
and how you can make your own.
</p>

<h2> Philosophy </h2>

<p> 
First and foremost, I wanted this site to be minimal. I'm a fan of minimalism
in real life, and even more so when it comes to technology. As the ultimate challenge
(it's not actually that difficult), I decided to make my site with absolutely 0 JavaScript
and no external pings to other websites. I did this for a few reasons:
</p>

<ol>
    <li> No JS makes the site load faster </li>
    <li> People who disable JS can have the same experience </li>
    <li> No external pings makes the site load faster </li>
    <li> I don't like programming in JS </li>
    <li> It's just a fun challenge </li>
</ol>

<p> So, how did I actually accomplish this? </p>

<p> 
Well, vanilla HTML and CSS are surprisingly powerful just on their own. The entire interface
can easily be made with plain old HTML and CSS, which makes the site faster, more secure and
easier to hack on than a massive site with a JavaScript framework. Now don't get me wrong;
JavaScript is a very useful language, but it's simply not necessary for a site like mine.
</p>

<p>
The only real technical challenge I encountered with this approach was syntax highlighting 
for code blocks. Most options out there are done with JS, which is probably the best way to do it
but I needed to stick to my challenge. You can always add an insane amount of &lt;span&gt; tags everywhere
and style them with CSS, but that's far from the best option... or is it?
</p>

<p> 
Enter <a href="https://pygments.org/">pygments.</a> Pygments is a Python program for doing generic
syntax highlighting across several hundred different languages. The best part: you can export it to 
nicely formatted HTML for ease of use with CSS! For example:
</p>

<div class="highlight"><pre><span></span><span class="k">with</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">nixpkgs</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="p">};</span>

<span class="n">mkShell</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="n">buildInputs</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span>
        <span class="n">python39Packages</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">pygments</span>
        <span class="n">xclip</span>
    <span class="p">];</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</pre></div>

<p> 
If you turn off JavaScript in your browser, you can see you still get syntax highlighting. Isn't that awesome?
</p>

<p> 
Now, to use Pygments efficiently I decided to write a quick mapping in Neovim for a simple task. Here is the code snippet:
</p>

<div class="highlight"><pre><span></span>map(&#39;n&#39;, &#39;&lt;C-s&gt;&#39;, &#39;:!xclip -sel c -o | pygmentize -f html | xclip -sel c &lt;CR&gt; &lt;CR&gt;&#39;, options)</pre></div>

<p> 
If you have a Lua configuration for Neovim, you can just drop that in. When you press Ctrl + S, it will 
read the code from your clipboard, highlight it and convert to HTML, and then put it back in your clipboard
so you can just paste it wherever you want.
</p>

<h2> How I made the site </h2>

<p> 
Well now that we have all that out of the way, how did I actually create the site?
As I said before, this site was designed to be minimal. I didn't use any sort of mockup program like Figma, I 
just edited the design as I went along. For the HTML and CSS, I started out with a bare HTML template, figured out
how to work in my static site generator, and adding the styling. Simple as that. The source code for the website can
be found 
    <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/notusknot/notusknot.github.io">here</a>,
if you want to look at it. 
</p>

<p> 
The only unconventional thing I did to make the site was use a little static site generator that I wrote for myself
called bmanager. Basically, it's a Bash script that copies some files into the correct places. But because of the way I've written
it, the general workflow for writing a blog post goes something like:
</p>

<ol>
    <li> Write an article.html file with the content of the blog </li>
    <li> ./bmanager new title-of-post </li>
    <li> Push changes to repo </li>
</ol>

<p>Pretty simple, huh?</p>

<p> The source for bmanager can be found 
    <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/notusknot/notusknot.github.io/blob/main/bmanager">here.</a>
</p>

<h2> The future of the site </h2> 

<p> 
As of August 2021 (site's release), the site is of course functional, but there are still some things I would like
to add to it. For one, I would like to be writing the posts in Markdown or 
<a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/vhyrro/neorg">Neorg</a> with automatic conversions via
<a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/jgm/pandoc">Pandoc</a>. I would also want to create an RSS feed, a
TOR mirror, and maybe even a Gemini capsule. However I will never stray away from the intention of this site, and I
will always keep it minimal, privacy-respecting, and FOSS.
</p>

<p> That's about it. Thank you for reading :) </p>
    ]]> </description>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
